I visit the future for a living.
أكسب رزقي بزيارة المستقبل.
Not just one future,
لا أعني مستقبلاً بعينه،
but many possible futures,
بل العديد من سيناريوهات المستقبل.
bringing back evidences from those futures for you to experience today.
وأحضر منها دلائل لكم، لتعيشوها اليوم
Like an archaeologist of the future.
كعالم آثار للمستقبل.
like a new species of synthetically engineered bees;
كفصائل جديدة للنحل مهندسة صناعياً؛
a book named, "Pets as Protein;"
أو كتاب "الحيوانات الأليفة كبروتينات"،
a machine that makes you rich by trading your genetic data;
أو آلة تجمع لك ثروة بالاتجار ببياناتك الوراثية،
a lamp powered by sugar;
أو مصباح يعمل بالسكر،
a computer for growing food.
أو حاسب لانتاج الغذاء.
OK, so I don't actually travel to different futures -- yet.
حسناً، في الواقع لم أسافر إلى عدة أنواع مختلفة من المستقبل بعد
But my husband Jon and I spend a lot of time thinking
لكنّي وزوجي جون فكّرنا مطوّلاً
and creating visions of different futures in our studio.
وصممنا في الاستوديو الخاص بنا العديد من سيناريوهات المستقبل.
We are constantly looking out for weak signals,
حيث نتتبع باستمرار الدلائل المُهمّشة
those murmurs of future potential.
تلك التي تشير إلى إمكانات كامنة في المستقبل.
Then we trace those threads of potential out into the future, asking:
ثم نتتبعها إلى المستقبل الذي ترسمه، سائلين أنفسنا:
What might it feel like to live in this future?
كيف سيكون العيش في ذاك المستقبل؟
What might we see, hear and even breathe?
ماذا كنا لنرى ونسمع؟ وماذا كنا لتنفس فيه؟
Then we run experiments, build prototypes, make objects,
ثم نجري تجارب ونبني تصاميم أوليّة وأغراض مختلفة
bringing aspects of these futures to life,
هدفها إظهار جوانب من ذلك المستقبل
making them concrete and tangible
لجعله حقيقيّاً وملموساً
so you can really feel the impact of those future possibilities
لتتمكنوا من رؤية تبعات سيناريوهات المستقبل تلك
here and now.
هنا، الآن.
But this work is not about predictions.
ولكن لا علاقة لعملنا بالتنبوء بالمستقبل،
It's about creating tools --
إنما ينطوي على تصميم أدوات --
tools that can help connect our present and our future selves
تمكننا من وصل ذاتنا الحاضرة بتلك المستقبلية
so we become active participants in creating a future we want --
لنشارك بشكل فاعل في بناء المستقبل الذي نصبو إليه
a future that works for all.
مستقبل مشرق لنا جميعاً.
So how do we go about doing this?
فكيف نحقق ذلك؟
For a recent project called Drone Aviary,
بدءنا مؤخراً مشروع: "قفص الطائرات بدون طيار،"
we were interested in exploring
حيث تركز اهتمامنا على البحث في --
what it would mean to live with drones in our cities.
-- ماهية التعايش مع وجود طائرات بدون طيار في مدننا،
Drones that have the power to see things we can't,
لديها القدرة على رؤية ما لا نستطيع رؤيته،
to go places we can't
والوصول إلى أماكن لا يمكننا بلوغها
and to do so with increasing autonomy.
مع تزايد قدرتها على التحكم الذاتي.
But to understand the technology,
لكن لكي نفهم التكنولوجيا،
getting our hands dirty was crucial.
كان لابد من العمل بشكل عملي
So we built several different drones in our studio.
لذا بنينا العديد من الطائرات بدون طيار في الاستوديو،
We gave them names, functions and then flew them --
وسمّيناها وبرمجناها للقيام بمهام معينة، ثم أطلقناها
but not without difficulty.
ولكن لم يكن ذلك سهلاً،
Things came loose,
حيث تفككت بعض الأجزاء منها،
GPS signals glitched
وتعطلت إشارات الـ جي بي إس،
and drones crashed.
وتحطم بعضها.
But it was through such experimentation
ولكن مكّنتنا تلك التجارب من
that we could construct a very concrete and very experiential slice
بناء تصّور مثبت بشكل عملي
of one possible future.
لأحد سيناريوهات المستقبل.
So now, let's go to that future.
لنطّلع عليه الآن.
Let's imagine we are living in a city with drones like this one.
لنتخيل أننا نعيش في مدينة تحلق بها تلك الطائرات، كهذه مثلاً
We call it The Nightwatchman.
سمّيناها "الحارس الليلي".
It patrols the streets, often spotted in the evenings and at night.
حيث تقوم بدوريات في الشوارع، غالباً في المساء وليلاً.
Initially, many of us were annoyed by its low, dull hum.
في البداية، يُزعج طنينها الكئيب العديد منّا
But then, like everything else, we got used to it.
لكن بعد ذلك نعتاد على صوتها، كأي شيء آخر.
Now, what if you could see the world through its eyes?
ماذا لو استطعنا رؤية العالم من منظورها؟
See how it constantly logs every resident of our neighborhood;
وراقبناها كيف تسجل باستمرار جميع القاطنين في حيّنا،
logging the kids who play football in the no-ballgame area
وكيف تسجل الأطفال الذين يلعبون الكرة في المنطقة المحظورة
and marking them as statutory nuisances.
وتحددهم على أنهم مصدر للإزعاج قانونًا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And then see how it disperses this other group, who are teenagers,
وكيف تفرّق هذه المجموعة الأخرى من المراهقين،
with the threat of an autonomously issued injunction.
حيث تهددهم بإنذار قضائي يمكنها إصداره ذاتياً.
And then there's this giant floating disc called Madison.
وهذه طائرة أخرى عملاقة، سمّيناها "ماديسون"
Its glaring presence is so overpowering,
لها حضور برّاق مهيمن،
I can't help but stare at it.
لا يسعني إلّا التحديق بها.
But if feels like each time I look at it,
لكني أشعر في كل مرة أنظر إليها،
it knows a little more about me --
أنها تعرفني أكثر قليلًا من السابق --
like it keeps flashing all these Brianair adverts at me,
حيث ما تنفكّ تظهر لي إعلانات "بريان إير"
as if it knows about the holiday I'm planning.
وكأنها تعلم بالعطلة التي أخطط لها.
I'm not sure if I find this mildly entertaining
لست متأكدة إذا كنت أرى ذلك مسلياً قليلاً
or just entirely invasive.
أو تدخلاً صريحاً في حياتي الشخصية.
Back to the present.
لنعد إلى الحاضر الآن.
In creating this future, we learned a lot.
تعلمنا الكثير خلال إنشائنا لهذا المستقبل.
Not just about how these machines work,
ليس فقط عن كيفية عمل تلك الآلات،
but what it would feel like to live alongside them.
بل عن ماهية التعايش معهم.
Whilst drones like Madison and Nightwatchman,
فمع أن طائرات مثل "ماديسون" و "الحارس الليلي"
in these particular forms,
بالشكل التي عرضناه الآن تحديداً
are not real yet,
ليست حقيقية بعد،
most elements of a drone future are in fact very real today.
إلّا أن أغلب خصائص الطائرات بدون طيار المستقبلية، حقيقية اليوم
For instance,
فمثلاً،
facial recognition systems are everywhere --
تنتشر أنظمة التعرف على الوجه في كل مكان --
in our phones, even in our thermostats
فهي في هواتفنا وحتى في منظمات الحرارة
and in cameras around our cities --
وفي كاميرات المراقبة في مدننا
keeping a record of everything we do,
مسجلةً كلَّ ما نفعله،
whether it's an advertisement we glanced at or a protest we attended.
كلَّ إعلان ننظر إليه أو احتجاج نشارك به.
These things are here,
أجزاء المستقبل هذه موجودة الآن
and we often don't understand how they work,
ولكننا في الغالب لا نفهم كيفية عملها،
and what their consequences could be.
وماهية عواقب وجودها.
And we see this all around us.
وتلك مشكلة منتشرة حولنا
This difficulty in even imagining
حيث لا يمكننا حتى تخيّل
how the consequences of our actions today will affect our future.
عواقب أفعالنا اليوم على مستقبل الغد.
Last year, where I live, in the UK, there was a referendum
في العام الماضي، جرى استفتاء في المملكة المتحدة حيث أعيش
where the people could vote for the UK to leave the EU
على خروج المملكة المتحدة من الإتحاد الأوروبي
or stay in the EU,
أو بقائها فيه،
popularly known as "Brexit."
ويعرف بال"بريكست."
And soon after the results came out,
وبمجرد ظهور النتائج،
a word began to surface called "Bregret" --
ظهرت كلمة "بريجريت" --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
describing people who chose to vote for Brexit as a protest,
تصف الذين صوتوا للبريكست كاحتجاج،
but without thinking through its potential consequences.
دون التفكير في العواقب المحتملة ثم ندموا على ذلك.
And this disconnect is evident in some of the simplest things.
وعدم توقع العواقب المستقبلية لأفعالنا جلية فى بعض أبسط الأمثلة،
Say you go out for a quick drink.
لنفرض أنك ذهبت للتمتع بمشروب كحولي.
Then you decide you wouldn't mind a few more.
ثم قررت أن تتناول المزيد منه.
You know you'll wake up in the morning feeling awful,
عالماً بأنك ستشعر بالغثيان والتعب في الصباح،
but you justify it by saying,
لكنك تبرر ذلك بقولك:
"The other me in the future will deal with that."
"سأترك ذلك لذاتي المستقبلية."
But as we find out in the morning,
لكن كما نكتشف في الصباح،
that future "you" is you.
أن "ذاتك" المستقبلية هي أنت أيضاً.
When I was growing up in India in the late '70s and early '80s,
عندما كنت صغيرة السن في أواخر السبعينيات وأوائل الثمانينات في الهند
there was a feeling
كان هناك شعور
that the future both needed to and could actually be planned.
أن التخطيط للمستقبل كان ممكنا بل وضرورياً
I remember my parents had to plan for some of the simplest things.
كان لزاماً على أبويَّ التخطيط لأبسط الأشياء
When they wanted a telephone in our house,
فعندما أرادوا تركيب هاتفٍ في المنزل
they needed to order it and then wait --
اضطرّوا لطلبه ثم الانتظار --
wait for nearly five years before it got installed in our house.
انتظروا لخمس سنوات قبل أن يتم تركيبه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And then if they wanted to call my grandparents who lived in another city,
وإذا أرادوا الاتصال بجدّي وجدّتي الذين عاشوا في مدينة أخرى
they needed to book something called a "trunk call,"
كان عليهم حجز ما يسمى بالمخابرة الخارجية،
and then wait again, for hours or even days.
ثم الانتظار لساعات أو حتى أيام.
And then abruptly, the phone would ring at two in the morning,
ثم فجأة كان الهاتف يرن في الثانية صباحاً
and all of us would jump out of our beds and gather round the phone,
لنقفز كلنا ونتجمع حوله،
shrieking into it, discussing general well-being
ونحن نصرخ على الهاتف نسأل عن أحوالهم
at two in the morning.
في الثانية صباحاً.
Today it can feel like things are happening too fast --
اليوم يبدو وكأن الأحداث تتسارع
so fast, that it can become really difficult
لدرجة يصعب معها
for us to form an understanding of our place in history.
تصوّر مكاننا في التاريخ.
It creates an overwhelming sense of uncertainty and anxiety,
ويولّد ذلك شعوراً عميقاّ بالتوتر وعدم الاستقرار
and so, we let the future just happen to us.
يدفعنا لترك المستقبل يأخذ مجراه
We treat our future selves as a stranger,
بل إننا نتعامل معها كشخص غريب،
and the future as a foreign land.
ونتعامل مع المستقبل كمكان بعيد.
It's not a foreign land;
ولكنه ليس مكاناً بعيداً،
it's unfolding right in front of us,
بل إنه يتفتح أمام أعيننا باستمرار الآن
continually being shaped by our actions today.
متغيراً باستمرار بحسب ما نفعله اليوم.
We are that future,
نحن ذلك المستقبل.
and so I believe fighting for a future we want
ولذا فأنا أؤمن أن السعي لبناء المستقبل الذي نريد
is more urgent and necessary than ever before.
أصبح أكثر أهمية وإلحاحاً من أي وقت مضى.
We have learned in our work
تعلّمنا خلال عملنا
that one of the most powerful means of effecting change
أنّ أكثر طرق التغيير فعاليًة
is when people can directly, tangibly and emotionally experience
هي عندما نعيش بشكل مباشر وملموس بكل حواسنا
some of the future consequences of their actions today.
العواقب المستقبلية لأفعالنا اليوم
Earlier this year, the government of the United Arab Emirates invited us
في مطلع هذا العام دعتنا حكومة الإمارات العربية
to help them shape their country's energy strategy
لمساعدتهم في تخطيط استراتيجية الطاقة لبلدهم
all the way up to 2050.
حتى عام 2050.
Based on the government's econometric data, we created this large city model,
فصممنا بناءً على بيانات الاقتصاد القياسي (econometric)، نموذج المدينة الضخم هذا
and visualized many possible futures on it.
حيث قمنا من خلاله بتصوير عدّة سيناريوهات مستقبلية.
As I was excitably taking a group of government officials
وبينما كنت أشرح بحماس لمجموعة من المسؤولين
and members of energy companies
وأعضاء من شركات الطاقة
through one sustainable future on our model,
عن أحد سيناريوهات المستقبل المستدام في نموذج المدينة
one of the participants told me,
قال لي أحدهم:
"I cannot imagine that in the future people will stop driving cars
"لا يمكنني تخيل مستقبل لا يقود فيه الناس السيارات
and start using public transport."
بل يستبدلونها بالمواصلات العامة".
And then he said,
ثم أردف قائلاً:
"There's no way I can tell my own son to stop driving his car."
"لا يمكنني الطلب من ابني أن يتوقف عن قيادة سيارته."
But we were prepared for this reaction.
ولكن كنّا مستعدين لردود أفعال كتلك.
Working with scientists in a chemistry lab in my home city in India,
وبالتعاون مع مجموعة من العلماء في مخبر كيمياء في مسقط رأسي في الهند
we had created approximate samples
جهزنا مسبقاً عينات غازية تحاكي تقريباً
of what the air would be like in 2030 if our behavior stays the same.
ما سيغدو عليه الجو في عام 2030 إذا ما استمر الحال على ما هو.
And so, I walked the group over to this object
فما كان مني إلّا أن وجهّت المجموعة إلى هذا الجهاز
that emits vapor from those air samples.
المصمم لينفث بخاراً من تلك العينات من الهواء.
Just one whiff of the noxious polluted air from 2030
نفثة واحدة من هواء عام 2030 الملوث بالسموم
brought home the point that no amount of data can.
أوضحت الفكرة بشكل أفضل من أي كمٍّ من البيانات
This is not the future you would want your children to inherit.
ليس هذا المستقبل الذي تودّ أن تورثه أولادك.
The next day, the government made a big announcement.
في اليوم التالي، أصدرت الحكومة إعلاناً كبيراً:
They would be investing billions of dollars in renewables.
ستقوم باستثمار مليارات الدولارات في المصادر المستدامة.
We don't know what part our future experiences played in this decision,
لسنا متأكدين من الدور الذي لعبه سيناريو المستقبل في إصدار هذا القرار
but we know that they've changed their energy policy
ولكننا متأكدون أنهم عدّلوا سياسات الطاقة هناك
to mitigate such a scenario.
لتجنب سيناريو مماثل له.
While something like air from the future is very effective and tangible,
ولكن في حين أن عينة هواءٍ من المستقبل دليلٌ دامغ وملموس،
the trajectory from our present to a future consequence
إلّا أن المسار الذي يربط الحاضر الآن بتلك التبعات المستقبلية
is not always so linear.
ليس بتلك البساطة.
Even when a technology is developed with utopian ideals,
فحتى عندما تُطوّر التكنولوجيا بأصفى النوايا والأهداف،
the moment it leaves the laboratory and enters the world,
حالما تخرج من المختبر للعالم،
it is subject to forces outside of the creators' control.
ستخضع لقوى خارج نطاق سيطرة مبتكريها.
For one particular project, we investigated medical genomics:
خلال أحد المشاريع، تحريّنا علم الجينوم الطبّي:
the technology of gathering and using people's genetic data
تكنولوجيا جمع واستخدام البيانات الجينية للإنسان
to create personalized medicine.
لتركيب أدوية تناسب كل شخص على حده.
We were asking:
وكنّا نسأل:
What are some of the unintended consequences of linking our genetics
ما هي العواقب غير المقصودة التي من الممكن أن تنتج عن ربط جيناتنا
to health care?
بقطاع الصحة؟
To explore this question further,
لتحرّي هذا السؤال،
we created a fictional lawsuit,
اختلقنا دعوة قضائية وهمية،
and brought it to life through 31 pieces of carefully crafted evidence.
وبلورناها على أرض الواقع ببناء واحدٍ وثلاثين دليلاً متقناً.
So we built an illegal genetic clinic,
بنينا عيادة جينية غير شرعية،
a DIY carbon dioxide incubator,
وحاضنة تعمل بثاني أوكسيد الكربون يمكن للمستخدم تركيبها بسهولة،
and even bought frozen mice on eBay.
حتّى أننا اشترينا فئران مجمدة على موقع eBay.
So now let's go to that future where this lawsuit is unfolding,
فلنذهب إلى سيناريو المستقبل حيث تتطور أحداث تلك الدعوة القضائية
and meet the defendant, Arnold Mann.
ولنتعرف على المُدّعى عليه أرنولد مان.
Arnold is being prosecuted by this global giant biotech company
يواجه أرنولد اتهامات من شركة تكنولوجيا العلوم العالمية الضخمة
called Dynamic Genetics,
دايناميك جينيتكس
that Arnold has illegally inserted the company's patented genetic material
أنه قام بحقن نفسه، بشكل غير شرعي، بمواد جينية
How on earth did Arnold manage to do that?
ولكن، كيف استطاع أرنولد فعل ذلك؟
Well, it all started
بدأت القصة
when Arnold was asked to submit a saliva sample in this spit kit
حين طُلب منه إرسال عينة لعاب في صندوق عينات اللعاب هذا
to the NHI --
لمؤسسة التأمين الصحي الوطنية
the UK's National Health Insurance service.
في المملكة المتحدة.
When Arnold received his health insurance bill,
وعندما تسلّم أرنولد فاتورة التأمين الصحي الخاص به،
he was shocked and scared
شعر بالصدمة والخوف
to see that his premiums had gone through the roof,
لأن دفعات التأمين تضاعفت بشكل هائل
beyond anything he or his family could ever afford.
بما يفوق قدرته أو قدرة عائلته المادية.
The state's algorithm had scanned his genetic data
فقد فحصت خوارزمية الدولة بياناته الجينية
and found the risk of a chronic health condition lurking in his DNA.
ووجدت بعد فحص حمضه النووي احتمالية إصابته بمرض مزمن.
And so Arnold had to start paying toward the potential costs
فوجب عليه تغطية التكاليف المحتملة للعلاج
of that future disease --
للمرض المستقبلي ذاك --
potential future disease from today.
أو المرض المستقبلي المحتمل ذاك -- من الآن.
In that moment of fear and panic,
ودفعه الخوف والهلع،
Arnold slipped through the city
للبحث في المدينة
into the dark shadows of this illegal clinic for treatment --
ليصل إلى ظُلمات هذه العيادة غير الشرعية، طلباً لعلاج
a treatment that would modify his DNA
يمكنه تعديل حمضه النووي
so that the state's algorithm would no longer see him as a risk,
لكي تكفّ خوارزمية الدولة عن تصنيفه كمريض محتمل،
and his insurance premiums would become affordable again.
وليتمكن مرة أخرى من تسديد أقساط التأمين.
But Arnold was caught.
ولكن، تم القبض على أرنولد.
And the legal proceedings in the case Dynamic Genetics v. Mann began.
وبدأت الإجراءات القضائية لقضية دايناميك جينيتكس ضد مان.
In bringing such a future to life,
خلال استحضار سيناريو المستقبل هذا
what was important to us was that people could actually touch,
كان المهم بالنسبة لنا أن يتمكن الناس من عيشه
see and feel its potential,
ولمسه ورؤيته والشعور باحتمال تحققه
because such an immediate and close encounter provokes people
لأن تجربة مباشرة وقريبة كهذه، تدفع الناس
to ask the right questions,
ليطرحوا الأسئلة الصحيحة،
questions like:
أسئلة مثل:
What are the implications of living in a world
ما هي عواقب العيش في عالم حيث
where I'm judged on my genetics?
يتم الحكم عليّ من خلال جيناتي؟
Or: Who might claim ownership to my genetic data,
أو: مَن من الممكن أن يدّعي ملكية بيناتي الجينية،
and what might they do with it?
وما الذي سيفعله بها؟
If this feels even slightly out-there or farfetched,
إذا بدى ما قدمته خارجاً عن المألوف أو مبالغًا فيه،
today there's a little-known bill being passed through the American congress
فاعلموا أن هناك مشروع قانون يمرّر الآن خلال الكونغرس الأمريكي، لا يعلم به الكثير
known as HR 1313, Preserving Employee Wellness Programs Act.
يعرف بHR 1313، أو قانون الحفاظ على صحة الموظف.
This bill proposes to amend the Genetic Information Nondiscrimination Act,
حيث يقترح تعديل قانون عدم التمييز بناء على البيانات الجينية
popularly known as GINA,
المعروف ب"جينا" "GINA"
and would allow employers to ask about family medical history
ليسمح للشركات أن تطلب معلومات حول التاريخ الطبي العائلي
and genetic data
والبيانات جينية
to all employees for the first time.
من جميع الموظفين. وذلك لأول مرّة.
Those who refuse would face large penalties.
وسيواجه الذين يرفضون غرامات باهظة.
In the work I've shown so far,
خلال الأمثلة التي عرضتها حتى الآن،
whether it was drones or genetic crimes,
من طائرات بلا طيار وجرائم الجينية،
these stories describe troubling futures
استعرضت قصصاً عن سيناريوهات مستقبل مقلقة
with the intention of helping us avoid those futures.
بهدف تحفيزنا على العمل لتجنبها
But what about what we can't avoid?
ولكن ماذا عن تلك التي لا يمكن تجنبها؟
Today, especially with climate change,
اليوم، خصوصاً مع الاحتباس الحراري،
it looks like we are heading for trouble.
يبدو أن مستقبلنا مليء بالصعاب.
And so what we want to do now is to prepare for that future
فعلينا الآن أن نستعد لذلك المستقبل
by developing tools and attitudes that can help us find hope --
من خلال تطوير أدوات وسلوك تساعدنا على العثور على الأمل --
hope that can inspire action.
أمل يحفّز العمل.
Currently, we are running an experiment in our studio.
نجري حالياً تجربة في الاستوديو الخاص بنا.
It's a work in progress.
لم تكتمل بعد.
Based on climate data projections,
بناء على تنبؤات مبنية على بيانات المناخ،
we are exploring a future
نتقصّى سيناريو مستقبل
where the Western world has moved from abundance to scarcity.
حيث انحدر العالم الغربي من وفرة بالموارد لانعدامها.
We imagine living in a future city with repeated flooding,
نتخيل العيش في مدينة بالمستقبل بها فيضانات متكررة،
periods with almost no food in supermarkets,
حيث تمر فترات من انعدام المواد الغذائية في المتاجر،
economic instabilities,
انعدام الاستقرار الاقتصادي،
broken supply chains.
وانقطاع سلاسل التموين.
What can we do to not just survive, but prosper in such a world?
ما الذي سنفعله في ذلك المستقبل ليس فقط لننجو، بل لنزدهر؟
What food can we eat?
ما طبيعة الطعام الذي سنأكله؟
To really step inside these questions,
لنتحرّى هذه الأسئلة جيداً،
we are building this room in a flat in London from 2050.
بدأنا ببناء هذه الغرفة في شقة في لندن عام 2050.
It's like a little time capsule that we reclaimed from the future.
ككبسولة زمن أحضرناها من ذلك المستقبل
We stripped it down to the bare minimum.
التزمنا في بنائها بالأساسيات فقط.
Everything we lovingly put in our homes,
فكل ما نحبه في بيوتنا
like flat-panel TVs,
كالتلفاز المتطور،
internet-connected fridges
والثلاجات المتصلة بالانترنت
and artisanal furnishings
والأثاث الحِرَفيّ
all had to go.
كلها غير موجودة.
And in its place, we're building food computers
ونبني بدلاً عنها، حواسيب غذاء
from abandoned, salvaged and repurposed materials,
من مواد مرميّة جرى جمعها وإعادة تصنيعها،
turning today's waste into tomorrow's dinner.
تحول ما يتم إهداره اليوم، إلى عشاء الغد.
For instance,
فمثلاً،
we've just finished building our first fully automated fogponics machine.
انتهينا لتوّنا من بناء أول جهاز بتقنية الزراعة الضبابية
It uses the technique of fogponics -- so just fog as a nutrient,
حيث يكتفي بالضباب كمادة مغذية في الزراعة،
not even water or soil --
وليس الماء أو التربة --
to grow things quickly.
لتنمية النباتات بسرعة.
At the moment,
حالياً،
we have successfully grown tomatoes.
تمكنا من زراعة الطماطم.
But we'll need more food than what we can grow in this small room.
ولكن ما نزرعه في هذه الغرفة الصغيرة لا يكفي،
So what else could we forage from the city?
علينا جمع المزيد من الغذاء من المدينة، فماذا سنجمع؟
Insects? Pigeons? Foxes?
حشرات؟ طيور؟ ثعالب؟
This time we are bringing an entire room from the future,
هذه المرة، سنحضر معنا غرفة بحالها من المستقبل،
a room full of hope, tools and tactics
غرفة ملأى بالأمل والأدوات والتكتيكات
to create positive action in hostile conditions.
لتحفيز العمل الإيجابي في البيئات القاسية.
Spending time in this room,
عندما نمضي وقتنا في هذه الغرفة،
a room that could be our own future home,
غرفةٌ يمكن أن تصبح مكان عيشنا مستقبلاً،
makes the consequences of climate change and food insecurity
تتجلى أمامنا تبعات التغير المناخي وانعدام الأمن الغذائي
much more immediate and tangible.
حاضرةً وملموسة.
What we're learning through such experiments and our practice
تعلّمنا من أجراء مثل هذه التجارب ومن عملنا
and the people we engage with
ومن الناس الذين نحتكّ بهم
is that creating concrete experiences
أن إنشاء تجارب عملية ملموسة
can bridge the disconnect between today and tomorrow.
سيعزز الترابط بين اليوم والغد.
By putting ourselves into different possible futures,
وعندما نعيش بأنفسنا سيناريوهات مختلفة عن المستقبل،
by becoming open and willing
ونكون منفتحين ومستعدين لتقبل
to embrace the uncertainty and discomfort that such an act can bring,
ما يأتي مع عيش تلك السيناريوهات من شك وقلق،
we have the opportunity to imagine new possibilities.
سنتمكن عندها من تخيل إمكانات جديدة.
We can find optimistic futures;
سنتمكن من إيجاد سيناريوهات مستقبل مشرقة،
we can find paths forward;
سنتكمن من شق طرقٍ للمستقبل،
we can move beyond hope into action.
وسنتمكن من الانتقال من الأمل إلى العمل.
It means we have the chance to change direction,
ستتاح لنا الفرصة لتغيير اتجاهنا،
a chance to have our voices heard,
ولإسماع صوتنا،
a chance to write ourselves into a future we want.
ستتاح لنا الفرصة لبناء المستقبل الذي نريد.
Other worlds are possible.
يمكننا بناء عالم أفضل.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)